<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-dt-iasa20-00.txt" ipr="trust200902">
<front>
   <title abbrev="IASA 2.0">IASA 2.0 Design Team Recommendations</title>

   <author fullname="Brian Haberman" initials="B" surname="Haberman" role="editor">
      <organization>Johns Hopkins University</organization>
      <address>
         <email>brian@innovationslab.net</email>
      </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Jari Arkko" initials="J" surname="Arkko">
      <organization>Ericsson Research</organization>
      <address><email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email></address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Leslie Daigle" initials="L" surname="Daigle">
      <organization>Thinking Cat Enterprises LLC</organization>
      <address><email>ldaigle@thinkingcat.com</email></address>
   </author>
    
   <author fullname="Joseph Lorenzo Hall" initials="J" surname="Hall">
      <organization>CDT</organization>
      <address><email>joe@cdt.org</email></address>
   </author>
    
   <author fullname="Jason Livingood" initials="J" surname="Livingood">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
      <address><email>Jason_Livingood@comcast.com</email></address>
   </author>
    
   <author fullname="Eric Rescorla" initials="E" surname="Rescorla">
      <organization>RTFM, Inc.</organization>
      <address><email>ekr@rtfm.com</email></address>
   </author>

   <date month="July" year="2017" />
   <area>gen</area>
   <workgroup>Individual Submission</workgroup>

   <abstract>
      <t>The arrangements relating to administrative support for the IETF were
      created more than ten years ago. There's been considerable change in the
      tasks and our own expectations since then. The IETF community has
      discussed these changes and the problems they cause. The community has
      some sense of the properties they expect from future arrangements,
      including structural and organizational changes, changes to volunteer and
      staff personnel resources, and transparency changes.</t>

      <t>This document is a product of a design team, focused on providing
      additional information to the community about solution options, as well as
      supporting analysis of the implications of those options.  To be clear,
      the community is in charge of adopting any recommendations or making any
      decisions.</t>
   </abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
   <t>The arrangements relating to administrative support for the IETF 
      (IASA <xref target="RFC4071"/>) were created more than ten years ago,
      when the IETF initially took charge of its own administration. The 
      arrangements have reasonably served the IETF, but there's been considerable
      change in the necessary tasks, in the world around us, and our own
      expectations since the creation of the IASA. What administrative arrangements
      best support the IETF in the next ten years?</t>

   <t>The system has experienced various challenges and frustrations along the 
      way, for instance around meeting arrangements. There are also some bigger 
      questions about how the organisations are structured, for instance about the 
      division of responsibilities between IETF and ISOC.</t>

   <t>The IETF community has discussed and continues to discuss these topics, most 
      recently on the "IASA20" mailing list and BOF at IETF98. Alissa Cooper, the 
      Chair of the IETF, asked a small design team to start evaluating potential 
      options going forward. The purpose of the design team is to provide material 
      that informs the community discussion, both in terms of providing a bit more 
      worked through solution ideas, as well as supporting analysis of the implications
      of those options. This information, along with all other input provided in the 
      discussion, hopefully helps the community and IETF leadership decide what next 
      steps to take.</t>

      <t>To be clear, the community is in charge of adopting any recommendations
      or making any decisions. This draft, the output of the design team's
      considerations, has no particular official standing.</t>

      <t>Once an initial version of this draft is published, the authors
      would like to ask feedback particularly on two aspects:
      <list style="symbols">
	<t>If the set of options outlined in the draft covers the
	options that should be looked at.</t>
	<t>If the analysis of the implications of the options is
	correct.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>Once this discussion completes, it becomes feasible to discuss what the
      conclusions or recommendations ought to be, and which recommendations the
      community should adopt. It should also be noted that IETF administrative
      matters have been organised jointly with ISOC, and it is important that
      ISOC is also involved in the process of looking at the reorganisation.</t>

   <t>As a base for this work there was a good articulation of the set of problems we
      are facing in <xref target="I-D.hall-iasa20-workshops-report"/> and
      <xref target="I-D.daigle-iasa-retrospective"/>. The community discussion 
      seems have indicated also some of the outcome properties that are expected.
      The scope of the solutions explored included:

<list style="symbols">
   <t>Structural and organizational changes, both externally (with ISOC and contractors)
      and internally (within the IAOC and subcommittees)</t>
   <t>Changes to personnel resources, both volunteer and paid</t>
   <t>Transparency changes</t>
</list></t>

<t>Changes to the funding model are out of scope to the extent they fall outside the
   categories above.</t>

<t>The rest of the document is organised as follows. The next two sections describe 
   the background and summarise the challenges noted in the community discussion. 
   The two sections after that explain what categories of changes were considered, 
   and describe the primary options for structural changes. The following section 
   discusses other changes, followed by two sections on analysis of the different 
   options along with a recommendation.</t>
</section>

<section title="Background">

<t>The administrative support structure intended to be responsive to the administrative 
   needs of the IETF technical community.</t>

<t>RFC 4071 <xref target="RFC4071" /> defines the current IETF Administrative Support 
   Activity (IASA). It is an activity housed within the Internet Society (ISOC), as is 
   the rest of the IETF.  RFC 4071 defines the roles and responsibilities of the IETF
   Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC), the IETF Administrative Director (IAD), 
   and ISOC in the fiscal and administrative support of the IETF standards process.  
   It also defines the membership and selection rules for the IAOC.</t>

<t>As RFC 4071 notes, IASA is distinct from IETF-related technical functions, such 
   as the RFC Editor, the IANA, and the IETF standards process itself.  The IASA has 
   no influence on the technical decisions of the IETF or on the technical contents 
   of IETF work.</t>

<t>Today, IASA's activities support a number of functions within the IETF system:

<list style="symbols">
   <t>Meeting planning</t>
   <t>Contracting with and overseeing the secretariat</t>
   <t>Contracting with the overseeing the RFC Editor (together with IAB)</t>
   <t>Contracting with and overseeing IANA (together with IAB)</t>
   <t>Legal ownership of IETF materials, domain names and copyright</t>
   <t>Ownership of IANA-related domain names and copyright</t>
   <t>IETF website</t>
   <t>IETF IT services</t>
   <t>Tooling support, maintenance, and development (together with volunteers)</t>
   <t>Meeting network support</t>
   <t>Remote attendance support</t>
   <t>Communications assistance for the IETF</t>
   <t>Sponsorship and funding (together with ISOC)</t>
</list></t>

<section title="Terminology">

<t>The following acronyms are used in this document:

<list style="symbols">
   <t>IASA - IETF Administrative Support Activity - An organized activity that provides a
      dministrative support for the IETF, the IAB and the IESG.</t>
   <t>IAOC - IETF Administrative Oversight Committee in the current IASA system - A largely 
      IETF-selected committee that oversees and directs IASA.  Accountable to the IETF 
      community.</t>
   <t>IAOC committees - Recognizing the need for specialized attention for different 
      branches of work requiring IAOC oversight, the IAOC expanded its support by creating
      committees. Currently, the committees do the heavy lifting on background work, while 
      the IAOC is the one responsible for final decisions.</t>
   <t>ISOC - The Internet Society - An organizational home of the IETF, and one that in the 
      current IASA system assists the IETF with legal, administrative, and funding tasks.</t>
   <t>IAD - IETF Administrative Director - In the current system, the sole staff member 
      responsible for carrying out the work of the IASA.  An ISOC employee.</t>
   <t>IETF Trust - In the current system the IETF Trust acquires, maintains, and licenses 
      intellectual and other property used in connection with the administration of the IETF. 
      Same composition as IAOC.</t>
</list></t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="challenges" title="Challenges">

   <t>Discussion leading to this document has been framed by the issues discussed on IETF 
      mailing lists and documented elsewhere  <xref target="I-D.daigle-iasa-retrospective"/>,
      <xref target="I-D.hall-iasa20-workshops-report"/>, 
      <xref target="I-D.arkko-ietf-iasa-thoughts"/>.  The reader is referred to those 
      documents and ongoing discussion on the IASA20@ietf.org mailing list for fuller 
      details on the range of challenges facing the IETF in its handling of administrative
      matters.</t>

<t>In summary, the key areas of challenge that have shaped this work are:

<list style="symbols">
   <t>The range of IETF administrative tasks has grown considerably; ensure we 
      have the right structure, community involvement and level of staffing to 
      address them effectively and efficiently.</t>
   <t>The relationship and division of responsibilities between the IETF and ISOC, 
      as both organizations have grown considerably in the last decade.
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The joint organisation that supports the IETF has grown rather organically, and
      would benefit from re-assessment and possible reorganisation.
   </t>
   <t>Alignment of community expectations of transparency of administrative actions 
      and delivery from the administration.</t>
   <t>Funding and sponsorships. Manage expectations about locations of meetings 
      (broadening of IETF engagement, sponsor preferences), balanced against 
      operational practicalities.  Ensure that we continue to not be influenced by 
      funding entities on the technical work of the IETF.</t>
</list></t>

   <t>Of the items above, the first two are largely to be addressed by structural
      updates, while the last two groups are more about discussing tradeoffs and 
      updating documented expectations.</t>
</section>

<section title="Considering a Change">

   <t>Given that a change seems necessary, what might that change include? There 
      seems three broad categories of IETF organisation that are going to be affected:

<list style="numbers">
  <t>overall structure,</t>
  <t>oversight, and</t>
  <t>interfaces and expectations to rest of the IETF.</t>
</list></t>

  <t>Overall structure includes also questions such as whether IETF is an organisation, and its the relationship to ISOC is.</t>

   <t>There are some interconnections between different aspects of
   reorganisation. For instance, how IETF defines its relationship to ISOC will
   have some implications on what kind of oversight structure is needed, for
   insance. And a more independent, free-standing organisational model for IETF
   would imply new functions at IASA.</t>

   <t>There are a number of choices to make within the reorganisation effort. In particular, 
      IETF's relationship to ISOC could be arranged in a fundamentally similar manner than 
      it is today, but improved, e.g., to make clear who is expected to control a particular
      part of the operation. But the relationship could also be arranged in a different way, 
      for instance, as a subsidiary of ISOC or as a more free-standing, own organisational 
      unit.</t>

<section anchor="goals" title="Goals">

   <t>The IASA redesign effort needs to address the main challenges listed above. More 
      specifically, a new organisational structure needs to do at least the following:

<list style="symbols">
   <t>Define the roles of the oversight entities and staff/contractors to match the grown 
      size of the tasks. Ensure that we have a structure that can adapt to future growth and 
      other changes.</t>

   <t>Define the roles of IETF and ISOC in a way that helps the above structure be as clear 
      as possible, in terms of who does what, how are things accounted, and who is in charge 
      of adjustments and control (e.g., staff resources). Propose a starting point for the 
      financial arrangements between IETF and ISOC, either as they are now or changed in
      some fashion. It shall also be clear to people outside the IETF and ISOC organisation 
      (e.g., sponsors) what the arrangements are and what their contributions affect and 
      do not affect.</t>

   <t>The new organisation needs to accommodate for strategic, operational, and execution of 
      administrative tasks, and take into account the limited availability of IETF volunteers 
      for performing administrative tasks. The new design needs to ensure that overload in,
      e.g., operational decisions does not affect the ability to drive strategic changes.</t>

   <t>Set expectations and limits of those expectations on the different parts of the system. 
      This includes, but is not limited to community expectations of transparency.</t>

   <t>Ensure that future IASA organizational structure and processes preserves and protects 
      the IETF's unique culture of individual contribution, clear separation of financial 
      support from technical work, as well as rough consensus and running code.</t>
</list></t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Reorganisation Options">

  <section title="Overall Structure">

    <t>The design team, in discussion with the IETF chair, believes that there
    are three general approaches to evolving the IASA function. The options
    generally focus on the relationship between the IETF and ISOC. Changes to
    this relationship directly affect how the IASA function gets carried out. It
    should be noted that all three options require more administrative budget
    per annum than what is currently allocated for IASA functions. The following
    subsections describe each option and highlights the pros and cons.</t>
    
    <section title="IASA++">
  
      <t>In the IASA++ option, the IETF and ISOC maintain the current structural
      relationship.  This means that the IETF remains an organized activity of
      ISOC, ISOC maintains funds and contracting authority on behalf of the
      IETF, and all IASA staff are ISOC employees.</t>

      <t>While the relationship remains the same, the IETF and ISOC will make
      improvements to the relationship in order to enhance the functionality of the
      IETF. The following are some potential improvements that could be made under
      this approach:

      <list style="symbols">
	<t>Provide clarity and transparency about authority, responsibility,
	budgeting, and allocation of staff time for all IETF-related work and
	activities.</t>
	<t>Add IASA staff.</t>
	<t>Provide clarity about authority of the IAOC in reviewing performance
	of IASA staff.</t>
	<t>Re-structure the internal IETF organization and appointment processes
	for the IAOC and the IETF Trust to address current challenges.</t>
	<t>Establish IETF community consensus about who has policy authority for
	administrative decisions where there is currently a lack of clarity.</t>
	<t>Improve IAOC transparency.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t><xref target="IASA-assess" /> highlights the pros and cons of the IASA++ option.</t>

      <texttable anchor="IASA-assess" style="all" title="IASA++ Pros and Cons">
	<ttcol align="left">Pros</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="left">Cons</ttcol>
	<c>Maintains familiar structures and relationships</c>
	<c>Does not provide the IETF with true independence of funding or staff from ISOC</c>
	<c>Start-up costs limited to those associated with hiring additional staff</c>
	<c>Creates risk that challenges present in current IASA will not actually be solved or will
	re-emerge over time</c>
	<c>Does not require legal and administrative work to incorporate a new entity</c>
	<c>Potentially requires ISOC to cede more authority to the IETF community or increase 
	transparency beyond ISOC's comfort zone</c>
	<c>Allows IETF to continue to rely on ISOC to somewhat frictionlessly compensate for 
	budget shortfalls if necessary</c>
	<c></c>
      </texttable>
      
    </section>

    <section title="ISOC Subsidiary">

      <t>In this option, an ISOC subsidiary would be created as the new legal
      home of the IETF.  A subsidiary can have its own bank account, by-laws,
      charter, board of directors/trustees, staff, and corporate identity. As a
      subsidiary of ISOC, the IETF and ISOC can share overhead and
      resources. The IETF would rely heavily on contractors for most
      administrative tasks.</t>

      <t>As a subsidiary of ISOC, the IETF could eliminate the IAOC and replace
      it with a board of directors/trustees. Administrative decision-making
      authority would primarily with the administrative staff, with oversight
      provided by the board. Exception cases could be developed where board
      approval would be required to authorize strategic decisions.</t>

      <t>Other possible changes could include:

      <list style="symbols">
	<t>Eliminate the IETF Trust and have the IETF subsidiary assume
	responsibility for IETF IPR.</t>
	<t>Transfer existing ISOC funds earmarked for the IETF to the subsidiary
	bank account, and have future IETF income held in subsidiary bank
	account.</t>
	<t>Transfer existing IETF-related contracts between ISOC and contractors
	to be between the subsidiary and contractors.</t>
	<t>Multiple options to structure community involvement in administrative
	decision-making (e.g., committees organized by subsidiary staff).</t>
      </list></t>

      <t><xref target="Subsidiary-assess" /> highlights the pros and cons of the ISOC subsidiary 
      option.</t>

      <texttable anchor="Subsidiary-assess" style="all" title="ISOC Subsidiary Pros and Cons">
	<ttcol align="left">Pros</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="left">Cons</ttcol>
	<c>Forces some delineation of responsibility, staff, and funds between the IETF and ISOC</c>
	<c>Leaves open some potential for continued lack of clarity about authority and funding 
	between the IETF and ISOC</c>
	<c>Provides the IETF community with greater authority over IETF administration</c>
	<c>Potentially requires ISOC to cede more authority to the IETF community or increase 
	transparency beyond ISOC's comfort zone</c>
	<c>Can leverage existing ISOC legal structures and personnel to keep administratie work 
	required to incorporate subsidiary to a minimum</c>
	<c>Requires legal and administrative work to incorporate subsidiary</c>
	<c>Requires less IETF community volunteer time commitment to administrative matters than 
	current IASA</c>
	<c>Vests more decision-making authority in paid staff than under current IASA</c>
	<c>Allows IETF to continue to rely on ISOC to somewhat frictionlessly compensate for 
	budget shortfalls if necessary</c>
	<c>Start-up costs include costs of incorporating the subsidiary and re-organizing/hiring 
	additional staff</c>
	<c>Allows IETF to continue to leverage expertise of ISOC administrative personnel</c>
	<c></c>
      </texttable>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Independent Organization">

      <t>In this option, a new non-profit organization (e.g., IETForg) is
      created independent from ISOC as the new legal home of the IETF. IETForg
      would have its own bank account, by-laws, charter, board of
      directors/trustees, staff, and corporate identity. The administrative
      staff for IETForg could be kept lean and would rely on contractors for the
      bulk of administrative tasks. Minimally, the IETForg staff would be
      responsible for administration, development/fundraising, communications,
      and personnel management.</t>

      <t>As an independent organization, the IETF could eliminate the IAOC and
      replace it with a board of directors/trustees. Administrative decision-making
      authority would primarily with IETForg staff and contractors, with oversight
      provided by the board. Exception cases could be developed where board
      approval would be required to authorize strategic decisions.</t>
      
      <t>Other possible changes could include:

      <list style="symbols">
	<t>Eliminate the IETF Trust and have IETForg assume responsibility for
	IETF IPR.</t>
	<t>Transfer existing ISOC funds earmarked for the IETF to IETForg, and
	have future IETF income held by IETForg. ISOC would still be largest
	IETForg sponsor, if funding maintained at current projections.</t>
	<t>Transfer existing IETF-related contracts between ISOC and contractors
	to be between IETForg and contractors.</t>
	<t>Multiple options to structure community involvement in administrative
	decision-making (e.g., committees organized by subsidiary staff).</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t><xref target="Independent-assess" /> highlights the pros and cons of
      the independent organization option.</t>

      <texttable anchor="Independent-assess" style="all" title="Independent Organization Pros and Cons">
	<ttcol align="left">Pros</ttcol>
	<ttcol align="left">Cons</ttcol>
	<c>Eliminates all ambiguity about IETF having authority independent from
	ISOC over staff, funds, and decisions</c>
	<c>Start-up costs include legal and administrative costs to incorporate
	a new entity, hire new staff, transfer contracts and funds</c>
	<c>Provides the IETF community with potentially complete authority over
	IETF administration and funding</c>
	<c>ISOC's financial support for the IETF may be viewed as more tenuous
	if the IETF is a legally separate entity from ISOC</c>
	<c>Requires less IETF community volunteer time commitment to
	administrative matters than current IASA</c>
	<c>Ability for the IETF to rely on ISOC in the event of budget
	shortfalls may be more limited</c>
	<c>Allows for direct investment in small number of professional staff
	specifically tailored to the IETF's needs and culture, while continuing
	to rely heavily on contractors</c>
	<c>Vests more decision-making authority in paid staff than under current
	IASA (i.e., risks of capture)</c>
	<c>Provides opportunity to structure board in such a way to overcome
	current challenges with IAOC structure</c>
	<c>Requires more from board members than what is currently required of
	IAOC insofar as hiring and evaluating staff</c>
	<c></c>
	<c>Requires IETF to assume legal risk currently assumed by ISOC</c>
      </texttable>

    </section>
    
  </section>

  <section title="Oversight">

    <t>Oversight is obviously affected by what we decide to do with the
    relationship to ISOC. A bigger, more independent role for the IETF would
    require IASA boards to be designed for that.</t>
    
    <t>The design team believes the role of the community members serving in
    IASA needs to be kept at a level appropriate for volunteer service (see
    community role in <xref target="challenges"/> and limits in <xref
    target="goals"/>).</t>

    <t>But beyond this, there are a number of choices in division of
    responsibilities and the structure of the organisation. The key decision
    points are:

    <list style="symbols">

      <t>Whether the community representative or board control of IASA is at the
      level of individual administrative decisions (as it is today) or at a more
      traditional board control, i.e., strategic direction, budgets, and key
      personnel choices.</t>

      <t>Whether the interface to the community is via staff or a community
      representative or board function.</t>
    
    </list></t>
   
    <section anchor="optiona" title="Strategic Board">

      <t>In this option, the current IAOC is disbanded and replaced by a
      traditional oversight board, common in most non-profit organisations. This
      board, the IASA Board (IB), acts to set strategic direction for IETF
      administrative matters, sets budgets, provides fiscal oversight, provides
      high-level oversight about major new projects. The board is also
      responsible for hiring and assessing the performance of the Executive
      Director (the highest-level staff director, see <xref
      target="staffresources"/>).</t>

      <t>The board works with staff who is empowered to carry out the operations
      as directed by the board. The staff is responsible for operating within
      the limits set by the board, and are accountable to the board. Including
      being hired and fired as needed. The staff's responsibilities include:

      <list style="symbols">
	<t>preparing for and making decisions on their agreed and budgeted areas
	(for example, meeting venue decisions)</t>
	<t>operational execution of these decisions, including contracting with
	vendors</t>
	<t>communicating with the community</t>
	<t>development of the IETF's administrative operation, in consultation
	with the community</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t>The primary difference between this option and the current IAOC
      arrangements is that board acts at a higher decision level, and is not
      involved either in detailed decisions or discussions on individual topics
      with the community. These are tasks reserved for the staff, and the
      board's role is to oversee that staff performs appropriately in their
      role.</t>
   
      <t>The composition of the board needs careful attention. It is important
      to have regular IETF participants in the board, but at least some of the
      board members need to have skills and experience less common among IETF
      participants, namely non-profit management, budget experience, and ability
      to help make connections to raise money or provide advice about
      fundraising (all of which are pretty typical for a non-profit board).</t>

      <t>One potential model for populating the board is a Nomcom-selection for
      2/3 of the board members and selection by IETF and ISOC leadership for 1/3
      of the board members with a view for more outside, well-networked
      members.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="optionb" title="Strategic Board and an Advisory Council">

      <t>In this option, there is a board and staff just like in <xref
      target="optiona"/>, but in addition, an Advisory Council (AC) provides an
      interface to the community on matters that require assessing community
      opinion. For instance, the current polling of community feedback relating
      to potential future meeting locations could be one such matter.</t>

      <t>An advisory council canvassing and pulling for this information is
      probably a better approach than either freeform mailing list discussion,
      or the relatively opaque process that is currently used. Advisory board
      results could be documented in the same fashion as IESG documents
      documents last call results. Some IAOC site decisions have been done in
      this way, but not all, possibly due to lack of time.</t>

      <t>The advisory council would be comprised of IETF community members and
      selected by Nomcom, and would benefit from having either the IETF Chair or
      another IESG member as a liaison. The advisory council would not make
      decisions about how the IETF should run, but it would be available for the
      staff to consult whenever they needed a view from the community, and it
      would also be available to run community discussion processes or to get
      input from the community to funnel back to the staff. The advisory council
      would have a well-defined interface to the IESG as well.</t>

      <t>The separation of the board and the advisory council, with some overlap
      between them, allows the allocation of people to tasks according to their
      skills. We can have experienced managers involved in hiring, firing, and
      reviewing the Executive Director and overseeing the budget, while we have
      experienced community people giving the perspective of the community.</t>

    </section>

  </section>
  <section anchor="staffresources" title="Staff Structure">
    
    <t>The design team believes that staff resources need to increased or
    reorganised from one director to a few more specialised roles (see growth in
    <xref target="challenges"/>). And In addition, the team believes that future
    organisation for IASA may benefit from organising all resources under a
    clearer and more direct control of the IETF (see division of
    responsibilities in <xref target="challenges"/> and roles in <xref
    target="goals"/>).</t>
    
    <t>The current arrangement involves one officially designated IASA employee,
    but there are also many supporting employees. They are less clearly assigned
    for the IETF, working at contractors and at ISOC.</t>

    <t>This document suggests a structure that involves:

    <list style="symbols">

      <t>An Executive Director. The person in this role is in charge of the
      overall IASA effort, but can rely on other staff members below as well as
      contractors. The Executive Director is accountable to the Board.</t>

      <t>Operations Director. This person is responsible for meeting
      arrangements, IT, tools, managing contracts (including RFC Editor and
      IANA), and day-to-day budget management.</t>

      <t>Partner Director. This person is responsible for working with IETF's
      sponsors and other partners, and the primary responsible for
      fundraising.</t>

      <t>Communications Director. This person is responsible for working with
      IETF leadership (incl. IETF Chair, IESG, and IAB) on communications
      matters, assisting them in efficient communication and dealing with
      ongoing communications matters.</t>

      <t>Legal Counsel (likely an outside counsel, contracted). This person
      assists the IASA on legal matters as well as prepares and reviews all
      contracts that are needed with IETF's contractors.  The Executive Director
      needs to be an employee, as are likely the other Director-level positions
      with the exception of the Legal Counsel.</t>

    </list></t>

  </section>
</section>

<section title="Analysis">

<t>This section provides a basic analysis of the effects of the different
options.</t>

<section title="Criteria">

<t>We use the following criteria based on the goals stated earlier:

<list style="symbols">

<t>The arrangements match the scale of the task (SCALE)</t>
<t>The arrangements are designed to evolve as situations evolve (EVOLVE)</t>
<t>Accommodates strategic tasks (STRAT TSK)</t>
<t>Accommodates operational and execution tasks (OPS TSK)</t>
<t>Avoids overload in one class of tasks preventing progress in other (OVERLOAD SEP)</t>
<t>Clarifies the relationship between IETF and ISOC (CLEAR ISOC REL)</t>
<t>Allows direct IETF control of resources (e.g., staff) working on a task (DIR CONTROL)</t>
<t>Preserves IETF culture and mode of operation (CULTURE)</t>
<t>Separates IETF technical work and administrative tasks and funding (WORK SEP)</t>
<t>Sets expectations on what can or can not be expected from IASA (IASA EXP)</t>
</list></t>

</section>

<section title="Internal Organisation">

<t>For the internal organisation, the implications of the current situation and the two 
   options are summarised in <xref target="Internal-Org-assess"/>.</t>

<texttable anchor="Internal-Org-assess" style="all" title="Internal Organization Implications">
   <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol><ttcol>Current Situation</ttcol><ttcol>Option A</ttcol><ttcol>Option B</ttcol>
   <c>SCALE</c>          <c>NO</c>             <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>EVOLVE</c>         <c>MAYBE (Note 1)</c> <c>MAYBE (Note 1)</c> <c>YES (Note 1)</c>
   <c>STRAT TSK</c>      <c>NO</c>             <c>YES (Note 2)</c>   <c>YES</c>
   <c>OPS TSK</c>        <c>YES</c>            <c>YES (Note 2)</c>   <c>YES</c>
   <c>OVERLOAD SEP</c>   <c>NO</c>             <c>YES (Note 2)</c>   <c>YES</c>
   <c>CLEAR ISOC REL</c> <c>n.a.</c>           <c>n.a.</c>           <c>n.a.</c>
   <c>DIR CONTROL</c>    <c>n.a.</c>           <c>n.a.</c>           <c>n.a.</c>
   <c>CULTURE</c>        <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>WORK SEP</c>       <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>IASA EXP</c>       <c>NO</c>             <c>MAYBE (Note 3)</c> <c>MAYBE (Note 3)</c>
</texttable>

<t>Note 1: Given that IASA is being reorganised, even the current system is capable of evolving.
   However, the operational focus and overload in the current arrangements are making this harder
   than is necessary. Change requires action from outside IASA, rather than being a normal task 
   within IASA to evolve their own model. Option A maybe a bit weaker than option B in evolution,
   given that in Option B there is a dedicated advisory council that can help determine community 
   concerns.</t>

<t>Note 2: There may be a difference between Option A and Option B in how overload situations 
   and the separation of different tasks goes. The existence of an advisory board may take off
   some board or staff load to deal with community opinion determination, freeing the board to 
   do its strategic work and staff to concentrate on operations and execution.</t>

<t>Note 3: Setting expectations is difficult merely based on an organisational model. 
   Certainly a clear separation between roles of the board and staff helps. However, 
   expectations are also a matter of documentation, which would have be created and 
   communicated. Finally, expectations are a cultural matter, current IAOC arrangements
   and community views have ended up in a situation where there is a lack of trust and 
   unclear models for what can or can not be expected.</t>

</section>

<section title="IETF-ISOC Relationship">

<t>For the IETF-ISOC relationship, the implications of the current situation and the three 
   options are summarized in <xref target="Relationship-assess"/>.</t>

<texttable anchor="Relationship-assess" style="all" title="IETF-ISOC Relationship Implications">
   <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol>
   <ttcol>Current situation</ttcol>
   <ttcol>Option 1</ttcol>
   <ttcol>Option 2</ttcol>
   <ttcol>Option 3</ttcol>
   <c>SCALE</c>          <c>NO</c>  <c>NO</c>             <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>EVOLVE</c>         <c>NO</c>  <c>NO (Note 4)</c>    <c>MAYBE (Note 4)</c> <c>YES (Note 4)</c>
   <c>STRAT TSK</c>      <c>NO</c>  <c>NO (Note 4)</c>    <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>OPS TSK</c>        <c>YES</c> <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>OVERLOAD SEP</c>   <c>YES</c> <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>CLEAR ISOC REL</c> <c>NO</c>  <c>NO</c>             <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>DIR CONTROL</c>    <c>NO</c>  <c>NO</c>             <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>CULTURE</c>        <c>YES</c> <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>WORK SEP</c>       <c>YES</c> <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>            <c>YES</c>
   <c>IASA EXP</c>       <c>NO</c>  <c>MAYBE (Note 3)</c> <c>MAYBE (Note 3)</c> <c>MAYBE (Note 3)</c>
</texttable>

<t>Note 4: Evolution in the current system is more difficult than if IETF was either clearly 
   a subsidiary or its own organisation. This would also ease driving any strategy that the 
   IETF wants to drive, as decisions would be more on the IETF side than something that 
   today would require negotiation with ISOC.</t>

</section>

<section title="Financial Impacts">

<t>There are two different classes of changes. First, both the ISOC interface change and 
   staff changes will imply changes in what is being accounted for in budgets and reports,
   even in cases where the actual work or the number of people stays the same. Secondly,
   there are actual increases.</t>

<t>We expect all the alternatives to lead to somewhat higher funding needs, and in fact
   shifting more work to staff from volunteers is one of the goals. For the internal 
   reorganisation, the primary position actually being added is having both Executive
   Director and Operations Director, instead of one IAD. We've already had Legal Counsel
   and Communications Director. These chances coincide with other personnel changes in IASA, 
   as the experienced, long-term IAD is retiring. Even from a learning curve point of view 
   more people will be needed, but in this case it also makes sense to have the organisation 
   be less dependent on one central person.</t>

<t>Given the learning curve effect, and a new organisation, it is expected that the role
   of the Legal Counsel will also increase, e.g., in terms of reviewing contracts.</t>

<t>The effects of ISOC relationship changes to finance are for further study.</t>

</section>

<section title="Other Impacts">

<t>Depending on the chosen option, volunteers are needed for either different roles than 
   today (the board) or for both different roles and more volunteers (the board and the 
   advisory council).</t>

<t>It is for further study whether current IETF leadership (e.g., IAB Chair) should 
   continue to be part of these boards or councils.</t>

</section>
</section>

<section title="Conclusions and recommendations">

<t>While there are some initial conclusions in the analysis in the previous
sections, clearly more work is needed. In particular, thoughts and contributions
regarding either missed options or their implications is welcome.</t>

</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">

   <t>This text is the work of the design team, but greatly influenced by discussions in 
      the IETF community. The team would in particular like to thank Alissa Cooper, 
      Andrew Sullivan, Ray Pelletier, Ted Hardie, Gonzalo Camarillo, Brian Carpenter, 
      Lucy Lynch, Stephen Farrell, Dave Crocker, Jon Peterson, Alexa Morris, 
      Michael Richardson, Olaf Kolkman, Kathy Brown, and Melinda Shore for interesting
      discussions in this problem space.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
   <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4071" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.daigle-iasa-retrospective" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.hall-iasa20-workshops-report" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.arkko-ietf-iasa-thoughts" ?>
   </references>

</back>
</rfc>
