<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-haberman-iasa20dt-recs-01.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IASA 2.0">IASA 2.0 Design Team Recommendations</title>

    <author fullname="Brian Haberman" initials="B" surname="Haberman" role="editor">
      <organization>Johns Hopkins University</organization>
      <address>
        <email>brian@innovationslab.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jari Arkko" initials="J" surname="Arkko">
      <organization>Ericsson Research</organization>
      <address><email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email></address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Leslie Daigle" initials="L" surname="Daigle">
      <organization>Thinking Cat Enterprises LLC</organization>
      <address><email>ldaigle@thinkingcat.com</email></address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jason Livingood" initials="J" surname="Livingood">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
      <address><email>Jason_Livingood@comcast.com</email></address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joseph Lorenzo Hall" initials="JL" surname="Hall">
      <organization>CDT</organization>
      <address><email>joe@cdt.org</email></address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Eric Rescorla" initials="E" surname="Rescorla">
      <organization>RTFM, Inc.</organization>
      <address><email>ekr@rtfm.com</email></address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2017" />
    <area>gen</area>
    <workgroup>Individual Submission</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The arrangements relating to administrative support for the IETF were
      created more than ten years ago. Since then, there has been considerable change in the
      tasks and in our own expectations. The IETF community has
      discussed these changes and the problems they cause. The community has
      some sense of the properties they expect from future arrangements,
      including structural and organizational changes, changes to volunteer and
      staff personnel resources, and transparency changes.</t>

      <t>This document is a product of a design team, focused on providing
      additional information to the community about solution options, as well as
      supporting analysis of the implications of those options.  To be clear,
      the community is responsible for adopting any recommendations or making any final
      decisions.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t>The arrangements relating to administrative support for the IETF
      (referred to as the "IETF Administrative Support Activity" (IASA) <xref target="RFC4071"/>) were created more than ten years ago,
      when the IETF initially took charge of its own administration. The
      arrangements have served the IETF reasonably well, but there's been considerable
      change in the necessary tasks, in the world around us, and our own
      expectations since the creation of the IASA. What administrative arrangements
      best support the IETF in the next ten years?</t>

      <t>The system has experienced various challenges and frustrations along the
      way, for instance around meeting arrangements. There are also some bigger
      questions about how the organizations are structured, for instance about the
      division of responsibilities between IETF and ISOC.</t>

      <t>The IETF community has discussed and continues to discuss these topics, most
      recently on the "IASA 2.0" mailing list and BOF at IETF98. Alissa Cooper, the
      Chair of the IETF, convened a small design team to start evaluating potential
      options going forward. The purpose of the design team is to provide material
      that informs the community discussion, both in terms of providing a bit more
      worked through solution ideas, as well as supporting analysis of the implications
      of those options. This information, along with all other input provided in the
      discussion, hopefully helps the community and IETF leadership decide what next
      steps to take.</t>

      <t>To be clear, the community is in charge of adopting any recommendations
      or making any decisions. This draft, the output of the design team's
      considerations, has no particular official standing.   It should also be noted that IETF administrative
      matters have been organized jointly with ISOC, and it is important that
      ISOC will continue to be involved in the process of looking at the reorganisation.</t>

      <t>The design team seeks feedback particularly on three aspects:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>If the set of options outlined in the draft covers the
        options that should be looked at.</t>
        <t>If the analysis of the implications of the options is
        correct.</t>
        <t>If the recommendations in <xref target="conc_recs"/> are a
	reasonable starting point re-organization work.</t>
      </list></t>

      	<t>This document defines the goals of the IASA 2.0 effort in terms of an abstract 
		administrative structure, called IETFAdminOrg.  Then, 3 possible implementations 
		of IETFAdminOrg are considered in the light of how they could be used to address 
		the goals.  In no case does IETFAdminOrg have anything to do with defining, 
		changing, or operating the IETF’s standards process and structure 
		(participants (not members), WGs, IESG and so on) which remain as they stand 
		today. In particular, none of the options change the role of the IETF as not
		being a formal organisation of any sort.</t>

      <t>As a base for this work there was a good articulation of the set of problems we
      are facing in <xref target="I-D.hall-iasa20-workshops-report"/> and
      <xref target="I-D.daigle-iasa-retrospective"/>. The community discussion
      seems have indicated also some of the outcome properties that are expected.
      The scope of the solutions explored included:

      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Structural and organizational changes, both externally (with ISOC and contractors)
        and internally (within the IAOC and subcommittees)</t>
	<t>Changes to funding arrangements (even if IETF continues to
	backed by primarily the same entities in the future as today).</t>
        <t>Changes to personnel resources, both volunteer and paid</t>
        <t>Transparency changes</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>The rest of the document is organized as follows. The next two sections (<xref
      target="background" /> and <xref target="problemstmt" />) describe the background and summarize
      the challenges noted in the community discussion.  The two sections after that (<xref
      target="goals" /> and <xref target="reorg_options" />) describe the goals and primary options
      for changes. The following two sections (<xref target="analysis" /> and <xref
      target="conc_recs" />) focus on analysis of the different options along with conclusions.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Background" anchor="background">

      <t>The administrative support structure is intended to be responsive to the administrative
      needs of the IETF technical community.</t>

      <t>RFC 4071 <xref target="RFC4071" /> defines the current IETF Administrative Support
      Activity (IASA). It is an activity housed within the Internet Society (ISOC), as is
      the rest of the IETF.  RFC 4071 defines the roles and responsibilities of the IETF
      Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC), the IETF Administrative Director (IAD),
      and ISOC in the fiscal and administrative support of the IETF standards process.
      It also defines the membership and selection rules for the IAOC.</t>

      <t>As RFC 4071 notes, IASA is distinct from IETF-related technical functions, such
      as the RFC Editor, the IANA, and the IETF standards process itself.  The IASA has
      no influence on the technical decisions of the IETF or on the technical contents
      of IETF work.</t>

      <t>Today, IASA's activities support a number of functions within the IETF system:

      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Meeting planning</t>
	<t>Budget and financial management</t>
        <t>Contracting with and overseeing the secretariat</t>
        <t>Contracting with and overseeing the RFC Editor (together with the IAB)</t>
        <t>Contracting with and overseeing IANA (together with the IAB)</t>
        <t>Legal ownership of IETF materials, domain names and copyright</t>
        <t>Ownership of IANA-related domain names and copyright</t>
	<t>General legal support (including topics beyond domains and IPR)</t>
        <t>IETF website</t>
        <t>IETF IT services</t>
        <t>Tooling support, maintenance, and development (together with volunteers)</t>
        <t>Meeting network support</t>
        <t>Remote attendance support</t>
        <t>Communications assistance for the IETF</t>
        <t>Sponsorship and funding (together with ISOC)</t>
      </list></t>

      <section title="Terminology"  anchor="terms">

        <t>The following acronyms are used in this document:

        <list style="symbols">

          <t>IASA - IETF Administrative Support Activity - An organized activity that
	  provides administrative support for the IETF, the IAB and the IESG.</t>

          <t>IAOC - IETF Administrative Oversight Committee in the current IASA system - A largely
          IETF-selected committee that oversees and directs IASA.  Accountable to the IETF
          community.</t>

          <t>IAOC committees - Recognizing the need for specialized attention for different
          branches of work requiring IAOC oversight, the IAOC expanded its support by creating
          committees. Currently, the committees do the heavy lifting on specific tasks, while
          the IAOC is the one responsible for final decisions.</t>

          <t>ISOC - The Internet Society - The organizational home of the IETF, and one that in the
          current IASA system assists the IETF with legal, administrative, and funding tasks.</t>

          <t>IAD - IETF Administrative Director - In the current system, the sole staff member
          responsible for carrying out the work of the IASA.  An ISOC employee.</t>

          <t>IETF Trust - In the current system the IETF Trust acquires, maintains, and licenses
          intellectual and other property used in connection with the administration of the IETF.
          Same composition as IAOC.</t>

        </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="problemstmt" title="Problem Statement">

	<t>The purpose of this part of the document is to describe a few problem areas with enough
	detail to allow the comparison of potential IASA structure updates (among themselves, as
	well as comparison to the status quo) that must be addressed by IETFAdminOrg. 
		This is intentionally illustrative, rather than an
	exhaustive enumeration of all possible and perceived issues with the current structure and
	implementation. Nevertheless, the examples are concrete and real.  (For a fuller description
	of the perceived issues with the current IASA arrangements, see <xref
	target="I-D.daigle-iasa-retrospective"/>, <xref target="I-D.hall-iasa20-workshops-report"/>,
	<xref target="I-D.arkko-ietf-iasa-thoughts"/>, and ongoing discussion on the iasa20@ietf.org
	mailing list.</t>

       <t>In general, the range of IETF administrative tasks have grown considerably, our
       organizational structure is not as clear, efficient, or as fully resourced as it should be,
       the division of responsibilities between the IETF and ISOC continues to evolve, expectations
       on transparency have changed, and we face continued challenges related to funding IETF
       activities on a background of increasing costs and lack of predictability in our funding
       streams.</t>

      <section title="Lack of Clarity">

	  <t>In general, as the IETF has grown and aged, an increasing
	  lack of clarity exists in a number of specific areas. We
	  discuss four areas where this lack of clarity is
	  specifically acute: responsibility, representation,
	  authority, and oversight.</t>

	  <section title="Responsibility">

	    <t>The line between the IETF and ISOC is not
	    organizationally clear-cut, which has led to issues around
	    transparency, allocation of staff time and priorities,
	    budgeting, and clarity of who is responsible for what.</t>

	    <t>Often, in can be unclear what part of the IETF or ISOC
	    is responsible for a particular function. Things as simple
	    as ensuring there is a lanyard sponsor/coordinator, but
	    also functions as important as fundraising and sponsorship
	    development can suffer from a lack of clear
	    responsibility.</t>
		  
	    <t>IETFAdminOrg must have lines of responsibility that are 
		    clear enough for non-IETFers to understand where 
		    responsibilities lie, and how to make changes as 
		    necessary over time.</t>

	  </section>

	  <section title="Representation">

	    <t>The respective roles of ISOC, the IETF chair, the IAOC,
	    and the secretariat in representing the IETF to sponsors
	    and donors and communicating with them are not clear.</t>

	    <t>Having ISOC represent the IETF to sponsors and donors:

	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>creates confusion about why the IETF does not
	      represent itself,</t>
	      <t>yields questions about why ISOC does not instead
	      increase its IETF support and how donations can be
	      guaranteed to be dedicated to the IETF, and</t>
	      <t>can result in those soliciting sponsorships and
	      donations having a lack of familiarity with IETF
	      work.</t>
	      <t>IETFAminOrg must have an integrated and 
		      understandable representation mode.  
		      People not familiar with the IETF 
		      (e.g., potential sponsors) must be able 
		      to recognize when or how an entity speaks 
		      for the IETF.</t>
	    </list>
	    </t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Authority">
	    <t>Another significant problem concerns authority, and to
	    what extent can IETF make decisions on its own in the
	    current structure compared to decisions that require ISOC
	    approval and agreement.</t>

	    <t>Example: Due to IETF's lack of legal status,
	    contractual agreements must be signed by ISOC on behalf of
	    the IETF.  There are occasions when a decision that is
	    right for the IETF and desired by IETF leadership cannot
	    be executed due to constraints posed by what ISOC can and
	    cannot agree to itself. For example, when IETF sought to
	    acquire a recent piece of software for business purposes,
	    ISOC would initially not agree to entering into an
	    agreement with the software provider. Ideally, IETF could
	    make decisions free from operational and other constraints
	    imposed by its relationship with ISOC.</t>
		  
	   <t>IETFAdminOrg must have enough and appropriate authority 
		   to carry out the IETF’s administrative requirements 
		   and activities in a timely fashion, and as the IETF 
		   desires (within reason of normal business and legal 
		   requirements).</t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Oversight">
	    <t>The IAOC is the primary oversight body in the current
	    IASA model, but there can be confusion or mismatches in
	    roles. For example, the IAOC has an administrative staffer
	    that is an ISOC employee, but does this role ultimately
	    report to the IAOC committee, the IAD, or ISOC staff? Even
	    if the reporting line for this staffer were more clear,
	    clearly there are power dynamics in this role that might
	    pull an ISOC-assigned IETF staffer in directions that
	    might not be in the best interests of IETF, consciously or
	    unconsciously.</t>
	  </section>

	</section>

	<section title="Lack of Resources">
	  <t>IETF faces growing constraints on resources essential for
	  IETF to function, notably in volunteers and staff.</t>

	  <section title="Volunteers">
	    <t>As the IAD is the sole FTE for IETF, naturally the IASA
	    arrangement has evolved to encompass a series of volunteer
	    committees that help to work through issues such as
	    finance, legal, meetings, technology management, requests
	    for proposals, and sponsorship.  Volunteers have limited
	    time and specific interests and there does not ever seem
	    to be enough volunteers to effectively populate these
	    committees.</t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Staff">
	    <t>IETF faces serious constraints on staff capacity under
	    the current IASA model. The one IAD role and support from
	    contractors have been used to assure that capacity needed
	    is for the most part in place. However, it seems clear
	    that the IAD role is overly complex and taxing for a
	    single human at this point, necessitating measures such as
	    providing an administrator for the IAOC to better run that
	    body and their meetings.</t>
	  </section>

	</section>

	<section title="Lack of Transparency">
	  <t>IAOC has typically been perceived to operate less
	  transparently than what is the norm for IETF processes and
	  other IETF leadership bodies.</t>

	  <t>Lack of transparency has some roots in concerns about
	  confidentiality of contract terms and business
	  relationships, and fear of community reaction to
	  administrative decisions.</t>

	  <t>Requirements from the community about IAOC transparency
	  expectations are not clear.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Funding/Operating Model Mismatch and Rising Costs">

	  <t>Meeting fees are currently an important source of
	  revenue, but the emergence of more viable remote participation tools
		  and other factors are likely
	  responsible for declining in-person meeting attendance going
	  forward.  Even if fees were charged for remote
	  participation, charging the same for remote and in-person
	  attendance is unlikely to be a viable way to make up the
	  difference.</t>

	  <t>While there has been a lot of sponsor support for, e.g.,
	  meeting hosting, getting support for the full costs of operating the IETF
	   is not easy.  The costs are quite large, the value to sponsors is not always
	  obvious, the IETF community is sometimes critical or
	  unappreciative, and the same sponsors get tapped again and
	  again for many related but different opportunities.</t>

	  <t>In addition, relying heavily on meeting-based revenue is somewhat at
	  odds with the fact that much of the IETF's work takes place
	  outside of in- person meetings.</t>

	  <t>The IETF is increasingly relying on professional services
	  to support its activities, in order to more efficiently operate the IETF's
		  activities better enable IETF participants to contribute to the IETF's
		  core technical work rather than administrative and supporting activities work,
		  which is also causing expenses to grow.</t>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="goals" title="Goals">

        <t>The IASA redesign effort needs to address the main issues listed above in the <xref target="problemstmt"/>. More
        specifically, a new organizational structure needs to do at least the following:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Protect the IETF's Culture and Technical Work: Ensure that future IASA organizational structure and
		  processes preserves and protects the IETF's unique culture of individual contribution, clear
		  separation of financial support from technical work, as well as the "rough consensus and running code" approach to
		  the development of open Internet standards.</t>

	  <t>Improve the IETF's Technical Environment: Undertake changes to better enable technical contributors to focus more
		on that technical work and less on administrative work or support activities. This could for example mean directing more
		  financial resources towards the creation of new or improvement of existing tools, which might be produced by
		  contractors rather than solely by volunteers. As a result, volunteers could instead focus on developing the
		  standards themselves. Thus, if the core competency of IETF attendees and their reason of participating in the IETF
		  is to develop standards, then create an environment where they can focus exclusively on that activity and delegate
		  to contractors, staff, or other resources the responsibility for creating and maintaining tools and processes to
		  support this activity.</t>

	  <t>Define a New IETF-ISOC Relationship: Define the roles of IETF and ISOC in a way that helps the above structure be
		  as clear as possible, in terms of who does what, how are things accounted for, and who is in charge
		  of adjustments and control (e.g., staff resources). This also includes consideration of a new funding model
		  that takes into account the historical responsibility for the IETF that ISOC has had since its inception.</t>

	  <t>Define a New Long-Term Funding Model: A redesign needs to update and improve the financial arrangement
		  between IETF and ISOC. It must also be clear to people outside the IETF and ISOC organizations (e.g., sponsors)
		  what the arrangements are and what their contributions affect and do not affect.</t>

	  <t>Clarify Overall Roles and Responsibilities: Ensure that all staff, contractor, and volunteer roles are clearly documented.
		This necessarily includes documenting how each of these parties may interact or interface with one another in order to
		  conduct and support the business of the IETF. This also includes documenting key work processes, decision-making
		  processes and authority (such as pertaining to meeting venue selection), etc. A key objective is to minimize ambiguity
		and uncertainty so that it is clear who is responsible for what and who has the power to make certain decisions.</t>

          <t>Define Support Staff Roles and Responsibilities: Very clearly define the roles of the oversight entities and
		  staff/contractors to match the expanded work scope facing the IETF. Ensure that any changes create a structure that
		  can adapt flexibly to future growth and other changes (including changes in IETF community expectations,
		  such as increased transparency or more rapid decision-making).</t>

          <t>Re-Define the Role of the IETF Community in Relation to Administrative Activities: As the roles and responsibilities
		  for support staff and volunteer roles are clarified more precisely, the role of the IETF community in
		  relation to those staff and volunteer roles must be better defined. This should acknowledge the limited
		  time and availability of IETF volunteers, better defining expectations around oversight of and involvement
		  in strategic, operational, and execution tasks within the administrative efforts. The new design needs to
		  ensure that volunteers are not overloaded in such things as low level operational decisions, which can be delegated
		   to and handled by staff, and can instead focus on strategic changes, critical decisions, and so on.
		  In particular, this should focus on clearly documenting the lines between responsibility, representation,
		  authority, and oversight.</t>

          <t>Define Improved Transparency Requirements: The general level of transparency and information-sharing between
		  IETF administrative staff and groups to the IETF community must be improved. This includes improving the timeliness
		  of sharing of information and decisions, as well as seeking comment on prospective decisions. As the same time,
		  we need to reset expectations around delegated authority so that once staff or an administrative support organization
		  has been delegated certain authority it is clear that they are empowered to proceed in a particular area, so as
		to improve organizational efficiency, reduce friction, and improve the pace of work and decision-making. However,
		it is clear that enabling a group or staff to act within their delegated authority depends upon more clear definition
		of roles and responsibilities, on improved transparency, on improved communications, and on trust (which is
		  built upon all of those things over time).</t>

	  <t>Define a New IASA 2.0 Team: Determine what new IASA structure we need and define a transition plan from the model the IETF
		  has today to the new structure.</t>


        </list></t>
      </section>

    <section title="Reorganization Options" anchor="reorg_options">

        <t>The design team believes that there
        are three general approaches to evolving the IASA function. The options
        generally focus on the relationship between the IETF and ISOC. Changes to
        this relationship directly affect how the IASA function gets carried out.</t>

        <t>The first subsection that follows, <xref target="overallstructure"/>, describes each of
	the three	re-organization options.</t>

	<t><xref target="sec.ietf-relationship"/> discusses
	the relationship of the IETF administrative organization to the IETF. Clear definition of
	this relationship is particularly important in the reorganization options that involve
	the creation of new entities (subsidiaries or independent organizations) to house the
	administrative functions. The next section, <xref target="oversight"/> discusses
	the creation of appropriate oversight to a new entity. <xref target="transparency"/>
	discusses the approach to transparency, which is largely independent of other aspects of the
	reorganisation.</t>

	<t><xref target="staffresources"/>
	outlines the needs for IASA staff, and <xref target="funding"/> discusses what
	short term and long term funding arrangement changes are needed. Both staffing and
	funding arrangements are relevant for all reorganization options, but are of course
	somewhat affected by the chosen option.</t>

	<t>It
        should be noted that all three options require more administrative budget
        per year than what is currently allocated for IASA functions. In addition,
        they will most likely require a more predictable level of ISOC funding,
        rather than the current model of a base funding level combined with
        periodic infusions to cover shortfalls.</t>

	<t><xref target="analysis"/> highlights the
        pros and cons and effectiveness of the options in comparison to the goals stated
        earlier.</t>


      <section anchor="overallstructure" title="Overall Structure">

        <section title="IASA++">
          <t>In the IASA++ option, IETFAminOrg continues to be implemented as an activity within 
		  ISOC.   While addressing the requirements above, this does mean that 
		  ISOC maintains funds and contracting authority on behalf of the IETF, 
		  and all IASA staff are ISOC employees.</t>

          <t>While the relationship remains the same, the IETF and ISOC will make
          improvements to the relationship in order to enhance the functionality of the
          IETF. The following are some potential improvements that could be made under
          this approach:</t>

          <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Provide clarity and transparency about authority, responsibility,
            budgeting, and allocation of staff time for all IETF-related work and
            activities.</t>
            <t>Add IASA staff to better reflect the increased workload on what is
            now a single staff member.</t>
            <t>Provide clarity about authority of the IAOC in reviewing performance
            of IASA staff.</t>
            <t>Re-structure the internal IETF organization and appointment processes
            for the IAOC to address current challenges. IETF Trust to be kept separate from IAOC.</t>
            <t>Drive IETF community consensus on roles and responsibilities for administrative 
		    decision-making so it is completely clear what people or group has authority 
		    to make decisions, and what type of consultation, if any, should take place with 
		    the community in advance so as to eliminate the current lack of clarity and friction 
		    that exists today.</t>
	  </list></t>

          <t>The key focus in implementing this option would be sorting out the roles
          and responsibilities of the IAOC and ISOC. The IETF needs to be able to make
          its own administrative decisions independent of ISOC. Having a concrete
          separation of roles and responsibilities will allow each organization to
          develop their own internal policies that meet their different operational
          needs. It should be noted that the IETF needs to keep abreast of changes to
          ISOC policies to ensure that the working arrangement remains smooth. Some
          examples of where the IAOC needs autonomy from ISOC policies include:</t>

          <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Contract administration</t>
            <t>Spending authority limits</t>
            <t>Personnel decisions, including compensation</t>
          </list>
          </t>

	  <t>Some specific changes to make these improvements are discussed in
	  <xref target="oversight"/> regarding board and staff work divisions.
	  While in this option there is no need for a formal board, there is
	  still a need to redefine the role of the IAOC. The necessary
	  staff changes are discussed in <xref target="staffresources"/>.</t>

	  <t>It would also be necessary to improve IAOC transparency. In the IASA++ option,
	  in addition to the general improvement needs in this area, there is an added need
	  to continue the improvements relating to accurate accounting of resources
	  and actions on the ISOC side. This relates directly to the delineation of roles
          and responsibilities necessary for the IAOC to operate independent of ISOC. Improved
          transparency will allow the IETF community to be more aware of IAOC operations and
          decisions. Such changes to the IAOC will require changes to <xref target="RFC4071" />.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="option2" title="ISOC Subsidiary">

          <t>In this option, IETFAdminOrg is implemented as an ISOC subsidiary, which Le
          would be created as the new legal
          home of the IETF administrative operation, similar to how the Public Interest Registry (PIR) is
	  organized within ISOC. A subsidiary can have its own bank account, by-laws,
          charter, board of directors/trustees, staff, and corporate identity. As a
          subsidiary of ISOC, the IETF and ISOC can share overhead and
          resources. The IETF would likely rely heavily on contractors for most
          administrative tasks.</t>

          <t>In the subsidiary model, IETFAdminOrg would carry out the function in
          ISOC's mission of supporting the IETF. ISOC itself would no longer
          undertake specific actions to that end, other than supporting IETFAdminOrg. In this
          model, ISOC's role would consist primarily of committing to a fixed level
          of financial support for IETFAdminOrg </t>

          <t>As a subsidiary of ISOC, the IETF could eliminate the IAOC and replace
          it with a board of directors/trustees (see <xref target="oversight"/>).
	  Administrative decision-making
          authority would rest primarily with the administrative staff, with oversight
          provided by the board (see <xref target="staffresources"/>.
	  Exception cases could be developed where board
          approval would be required to authorize strategic decisions.</t>

          <t>As IETFAdminOrg would be a majority or wholly owned subsidiary of ISOC,
          ISOC would retain the ability to shut it down and re-absorb the
          functions at some future date. The founding
          agreements would need to include provisions to clarify the steps required in
          order to consult with the IETF community, provide an opportunity for
          the organization to become independent, etc.</t>

          <t>During the transition between the current model and this model, we would
          need to transfer all existing IETF administrative relationships from ISOC to
          IETFAdminOrg:</t>

          <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Transfer existing IETF-related contracts between ISOC and contractors
            to be between the subsidiary and contractors.</t>

            <t>Transfer existing ISOC funds earmarked for the IETF to the subsidiary's
            bank account(s), and have future IETF income held in that subsidiary's bank
            account(s).</t>
	  </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Independent Organization">

          <t>In this option, a new non-profit organization (e.g., IETFAdminorg) is
          created independent from ISOC as the new legal home of the IETF. IETFAdminOrg
          would have its own bank account, by-laws, charter, board of
          directors/trustees, staff, and corporate identity. The administrative
          staff for IETFAdminOrg could be kept lean and would likely rely on contractors for the
          bulk of administrative tasks. Minimally, the IETFAdminOrg staff would be
          responsible for administration, development/fundraising, communications,
          and personnel management.</t>

          <t>In the independent organization model, IETFAdminOrg's continued
          existence would not depend on the ISOC organization's choices about
          its future. However, IETFAdminOrg would still depend on the ISOC's support,
          for two reasons:
          </t>
          <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>ISOC is missioned to support the IETF [TODO: Citation needed].</t>
            <t>As a practical matter, IETFAdminOrg is not financially viable without
            ISOC's support.</t>
          </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            In order to establish this model, IETFAdminOrg and ISOC would need some
            sort of explicit agreement that outlined expected levels of financial
            support going forward, both in terms of founding endowments and in
            terms of ongoing support. These agreements might also cover IETFAdminOrg's
            obligations to ISOC, such as the level of reporting from
            IETFAdminOrg to ISOC, and the expected structure of any liaisons.
          </t>
          <t>
            As in the ISOC Subsidiary model, it would be necessary to transfer
            the existing relationships to IETFAdminOrg. See the previous
            section for details on this.
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section title="IETFAdminOrg and the Relationship with IETF" anchor="sec.ietf-relationship">
        <t>
          As noted above, currently the business side of the IETF is basically
          done by ISOC with the only formal entity being the IAD, which is
          itself a position within ISOC. In both the ISOC Subsidiary and
          the Independent Organization models, we would create a new
          organization ("IETFAdminOrg"), which would encapsulate the administrative
          responsibilities of the IETF organization in a new business entity.
          Its sole mission would be to ensure the IETF (standards) activities
          are appropriately supported and administered.
        </t>

        <t>
          "The IETF" would remain an unincorporated entity, pretty much just as
          we know it today, with the relationship between IETF and IETFAdminOrg being
          a more formalized version of the relationship between IETF and the
          parts of ISOC which support IETF:
        </t>

        <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t> IETFAdminorg would have as its mission to support IETF and would
          exist for the benefit of the IETF.</t>

          <t>The IETF would provide oversight into the governance of IETFAdminOrg,
          including seating part of the board.</t>

          <t>IETFAdminOrg would not have a say over the material direction or content of
          the IETF, except insofar as there are legal implications and
          requirements.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          Beyond negotiation, administering and managing the contracts necessary
          for the work to support the IETF, IETF org would also start with
          sponsorship and communications functions.  Different functions and
          services might be needed as the IETF evolves.  The implementation
          would be determined by the IETFAdminOrg Executive Director, but the need
          and direction has to be provided by the IETF (currently, through the
          IETF Chair, but one hopes the IETF might evolve a broader base for
          making the kind of strategic determination needed).
        </t>

        <t>
          IETFAdminOrg would be staffed.  It would be signatory to all
          IETF-supporting contracts.  It would collect financial support for the
          IETF, and administer the financial resources.  Its annual budgets
          would be reviewed and approved by its own Board of Trustees, which
          would be populated pretty much as any Board of Trustees (with the
          additional requirements in the notes below).  In all regards, it would
          be a self-contained organization, evolving to meet its mission based
          on its best governance choices to evolve, staff and execute.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="oversight" title="Oversight for IETFAdminOrg">

        <t>While IASA++ could have a relatively similar oversight structure to
        the existing IAOC, either the Subsidiary or Independent models involve
        the creation of an IETFAdminOrg which needs a more substantial government
        structure. This structure needs to include the involvement of members
        with significant nonprofit governance experience, while also ensuring
        accountability to and involvement from the IETF Community.
        </t>

        <t>In order to achieve these objectives, the design team proposes
        a model similar to other nonprofits, in which IETFAdminOrg would be governed by a Board of Directors.
        This board, the IASA Board (IB), acts to set strategic direction for
        IETF administrative matters, sets budgets, provides fiscal oversight,
        provides high-level oversight about major new projects, and so on.
        The board is also responsible for hiring and assessing the
        performance of the Executive Director (the highest-level staff
        director (see <xref target="staffresources"/>).
        </t>

        <t>The board works with staff who is empowered to carry out the
        operations as directed by the board.  The staff is responsible for
        operating within the limits set by the board, and are accountable to
        the board.  Including being hired and fired as needed.  The staff's
        responsibilities include:
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>preparing for and making decisions on their agreed and budgeted
            areas (for example, meeting venue decisions)</t>

            <t>operational execution of these decisions, including contracting
            with vendors</t>

            <t>communicating with the community</t>

            <t>development of the IETF's administrative operation, in
            consultation with the community</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          The composition of the board needs careful attention.  It is
          important to have regular IETF participants in the board, but at
          least some of the board members need to have skills and experience
          less common among IETF participants, namely non-profit management,
          budget experience, and ability to help make connections to raise
          money or provide advice about fundraising (all of which are typical
          for a non-profit board).
        </t>

        <t>
          One potential model for populating the board is a Nomcom-selection
          for 1/3 of the board members and some other type of selection for 2/3
          of the board members with a view for more independent, well-networked
          members. In addition, if we follow the ISOC Subsidiary model
          (see <xref target="option2"/>), then ISOC would likely nominate some subset of the board
          members. All members of the board should be subject to confirmation
          from the IETF, most likely via the IAB, though perhaps from the IESG
          or both. The details of how the initial board is to be constituted
          need to be determined, but one possibility would be to draw from
          the existing IAOC and IETF-selected ISOC BOT members, with the
          board replacing itself within a short period (strawman: two years).
        </t>

        <t>
          In addition to the Board, IETFAdminOrg would also have an "Advisory Council",
          which is drawn from the IETF community (in some TBD fashion). This
          council would have no formal decision-making responsibility but the
          Board would be expected to consult with the AC on matters strongly
          affecting the community. The purpose of the AC is to involve IETF
          members who have strong community ties but do not have the time or
          administrative experience to serve on a governing board.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="transparency" title="Transparency">
	<t>Regardless of the chosen Reorganization model, transparency deserves attention. As
	discussed in <xref target="goals"/>, this includes improving the timeliness
		  of sharing of information and decisions, seeking comment on prospective decisions,
	and a a "reset" of expectations around delegated authority.</t>
	<t>In addition, there needs to be an agreement between the IETF community and the
	administrative entity about the where to draw the line between community's need for
	information, and the need to keep some business (or personnel) data confidential. This
	document suggests a "default open" model, where all information is kept openly available,
	unless it belongs to an agreed list of exceptional information that needs to be
	confidential. An IETF process is needed to form that list of exceptions.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="staffresources" title="Staff Structure">

        <t>The design team believes that staff resources need to increase and/or
        be reorganized in order to move from one director to a few more specialized roles (see growth in
        <xref target="problemstmt"/>). In addition, the team believes that future
        organization for IASA may benefit from organizing all resources under the more
        clear and direct control of the IETF (see division of
        responsibilities in <xref target="problemstmt"/> and roles in <xref
        target="goals"/>).</t>

        <t>The current arrangement involves one officially designated IASA employee,
        but there are also many supporting employees. They are less clearly assigned
        for the IETF, working as contractors or at ISOC.</t>

        <t>This document suggests a structure that involves the following roles:

        <list style="symbols">

          <t>Executive Director. The person in this role is in charge of the
          overall IASA effort, but can rely on other staff members below as well as
          contractors. The Executive Director is accountable to the Board.</t>

          <t>Director of Operations. This person is responsible for meeting
          arrangements, IT, tools, managing contracts (including RFC Editor and
          IANA), and day-to-day budget management.</t>

          <t>Director of Fundraising. This person is responsible for working with IETF's
          sponsors and other partners, and his or her primary responsibility
          is fundraising for the IETF.</t>

          <t>Director of Communications. This person is responsible for working with
          IETF leadership (including the IETF Chair, IESG, and IAB) on communications
          matters (primarily but not exclusively external communications),
          assisting them in efficient communication and dealing with
          ongoing communications matters.</t>

        </list></t>
        <t>Note: The Executive Director likely needs to be a full-time employee,
        as is likely the case for the other Director-level positions.</t>

	<t>These persons also need to rely on a number of contractors
	and outside specialists. For instance, a Legal Counsel, to assist the IASA on legal matters as well as contracting.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="funding" title="Funding">

	<t>This section discusses the overall changes to IETF funding sources, the level of
	funding, and how the level of funding is agreed with ISOC. And how the IETF
	can further develop its funding strategies over time.</t>

	<t>None of the administrative arrangements proposed in this document suggest that
	the fundamental funding arrangements change as a part of the Reorganization.
	ISOC will continue to support the IETF, though perhaps with
	means that provide better budgetary stability. There are also factors that affect
	the level of funding. Also, a better administrative organization will be more
	capable of adjusting its strategies in the future in all areas, including
	funding. Any significant future changes require a capability of the IASA to
	focus on such strategic initiatives, which IASA 2.0 will help enable.</t>

	<t>It is important to ensure that IETF funding is arranged in a manner that is
	satisfactory to the IETF and ISOC communities. Any changes to arrangements are
	something that should be mutually agreed with both organizations. Further
	comments and observations are welcome.</t>

	<section title="One-time costs">

	  <t>There are one time costs associated with an administrative change, regardless of
	  which of the options discussed in this document are chosen. All the models in
	  the draft will have associated costs - e.g., to hire additional staff, cover
	  legal fees, etc.</t>

	  <t>Transition expenses should be considered separately from ongoing
	  expenses/funding needs. It should be noted that ISOC has promised to cover those
	  costs <xref target="Camarillo"/>.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Sources and Stability">

	  <t>The key sources of IETF funding are unlikely to radically change in
	  the short or medium term. This document suggests that ISOC continues as one of
	  our primary funding source, as it has been. Other primary sources of funding for
	  an organization like the IETF are well known, and we are already tapping into
	  all of the most common ones - corporations, individuals, and funds derived from
	  the registration of domain names. It is possible that we could develop
	  additional funding sources in the future (e.g., charitable foundations), but
	  those will require strategic planning and staffing, for which we need to get
	  IASA 2.0 in place first.</t>

	  <t>It's worth considering short-term (3-5 years) and long-term (5-10+ years) plans
	  differently. In the short term, we can continue to rely on our existing funding
	  sources regardless of which organizational model we end up with for IASA 2.0,
	  including the independent organization model. The role of ISOC as providing the
	  funding to the IETF and agreeing to help us if we get to trouble should stay
	  under all of the options, until or if a future funding model change changes
	  that.</t>

	  <t>While ISOC continues to support IETF financially as they
	  have previously, the different Reorganization options affect
	  the legal, contractual, and accounting related
	  details. While continuing as-is is possible, adopting a a
	  more stable and predictable allocation of funding is
	  desirable (see <xref target="fundinglevel"/>, and in the
	  subsidiary and independent options formal contracts about
	  the funding are also necessary. The exact details of those
	  contracts and contracting parties are for further study, but
	  they do not need to change the fundamental arrangement that
	  is in place today.</t>

	  <t>More long-term, developing a sustainable funding plan for the IETF will be a
	  key project during the early months and years post-IASA 2.0. Ultimately a
	  healthier funding model will require raising more funds from the organizations
	  that benefit from IETF standards and whose employees participate in the IETF,
	  and may result in less reliance on ISOC funds. Such a model might incorporate
	  meeting-based sponsorships as we have traditionally had, other kinds of
	  sponsorships, a fully funded endowment, a different registration fee structure,
	  or other funding vehicles. But we are not in a position at present to develop
	  such a model and carry out the fundraising. We do not have sufficient staff,
	  skills, or resources to do it. We need to complete IASA 2.0 in order to be in a
	  position to do it. We are fortunate that we can rely on additional funds from
	  ISOC in the short term in order to bootstrap that process. As the old saying
	  goes, you have to spend money to make money.</t>

	  <t>This isn't to say that the IETF not already considering how to make the funding
	  model more sustainable. The IAOC has new sponsorship staff this year, the
	  the IAOC sponsorship committee was recently chartered, and it has been discussing new ideas for raising
	  sponsorship funds. Changes to the present model will be adopted as those ideas
	  mature. IETF can cut some costs. But we can not expect
	  volunteers and folks working part-time on current fundraising targets to also
	  take on the additional substantial project of revamping the entire funding model
	  and having the additional funds show up on short order.</t>

	</section>

	<section anchor="fundinglevel" title="Level">

	  <t>Outside the discussion of sources, the level of funding has also been an issue.
	  The IETF is well supported by ISOC who have ultimately also been the backstop
	  when income has fallen below expectations. The IETF is also supported by a
	  number of other sponsors, whose significant contributions provide a big part of
	  the income.</t>

	  <t>However, at the same time there is an overall rising cost level that affects the
	  services IETF uses, there is community desire for supporting important new
	  services, technology that enables more participants to choose to participate
	  remotely, and industry pressures on optimizing their costs. As the organization
	  matures, and as more of the services that IETF provides come from professional
	  sources, it becomes more difficult to rely on significant fraction of any individual
	  volunteer time. This is visible, for instance, in our tools efforts, which have
	  become more commercially driven in the last years.</t>

	  <t>It is fair to say that IETF continues to be underfunded in the face of these
	  trends. In addition, IETF budgets have in recent years been relatively
	  optimistic. IETF is fortunate that ISOC has been there to provide a backstop
	  against surprises and the cost trends, but ideally, budgets should be realistic
	  and exceptions more exceptional than they are today.</t>

	  <t>To correct this, four things are needed:

	  <list style="numbers">

	    <t>Improve the accounting of IETF-related costs<vspace blankLines="1"/>

	    The process that has gone on for several years to better reflect actual
	    IETF-related costs in the IETF (and ISOC) budget will continue, and depending on
	    the chosen model, reach a much more concrete and clear structure. This will not
	    as such, however, change the actual amount of expenditure
	    or income.
	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>

	    Note that the IETF already accounts for the expenses related to key IETF support
	    staff (e.g., IAD, communications, etc).</t>

	    <t>Implement a more realistic budgeting process.<vspace blankLines="1"/>

	    Assumptions about participant numbers, for instance, and the amount of
	    sponsorship available per meeting need to reflect reality better.<vspace blankLines="1"/>

	    This should also involve appropriate decisions about what services
	    are essential for the IETF community and which are not.<vspace blankLines="1"/>

	    The improved budgeting processes have been a goal of the 2018
	    process, and need to be also going forward.</t>

	    <t>ISOC as a funder and backstop.<vspace blankLines="1"/>

	    ISOC continues to be the major IETF funding source, as well as the backstop
	    against emergencies. But a different arrangement regarding these two roles would
	    make the situation better manageable.<vspace blankLines="1"/>

	    Dedicated, realistically sufficient funds allocated to the IETF would allow the
	    normal operations to be run based on that, and would leave only true emergencies
	    such as cancellation of meetings due to local emergencies for the backstop.</t>

	    <t>Appropriate funding level.<vspace blankLines="1"/>

	    The IETF operations and funding level obviously need to
	    match. The specific level is, however, not related to the IASA 2.0
	    related organizational changes. Those organizational
	    changes only make it hopefully easier to manage both the
	    IETF operations and the funding.</t>

	  </list></t>

	</section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="analysis" title="Analysis">

      <t>This section provides a basic analysis of the effects of the different
      options.</t>

      <section anchor="comp-criteria-overall" title="Comparison to Goals">

	<t>In the following, we analyze how the different options compare with respect to goals set
	in <xref target="goals"/>:

	<list style="symbols">
	  
	  <t>Protect the IETF's Culture and Technical Work: <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  The changes under the IASA++ option are small enough that they clearly cannot have any
	  undue effect on culture or actual IETF work. <vspace blankLines="1"/>

	  The ISOC subsidiary and independent
	  organization models are bigger changes, but, still contained within the administrative
	  support part. To be exact, the IETF will not become an organization even if the
	  administrative support for it may. While one may have an opinion that administrative
	  functions may grow or acquire more staff over time (and there is always some danger of
	  that), keeping both the IETF and IETF Trust out of the
	  organization for administration does provide a level of separation. This separation
	  ensures that participant, working group, IESG, IETF Chair, and other similar roles should
	  continue to operate as they are operating now.
	  </t>

	  <t>Improve the IETF's Technical Environment:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  All organization options target improvements in this area. The options may differ in how
	  much freedom or organization agility they provide. Clearly, in the independent
	  organization option the IETF has most of these.</t>

	  <t>Define a New IETF-ISOC Relationship:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  Again, all options are forced to define this relationship in a clearer way than it is
	  defined today. However, the subsidiary and independent organization models
	  have a better ability to reach a clear definition. A clear definition is not merely a
	  matter of specification, it is also affected by practical and even legal constraints
	  and organizations' goals. For instance, for obvious privacy and legal reasons, IETF may
	  not have quite as much control and information about ISOC employees as it would on its
	  own administrative unit's employees.
	  </t>

	  <t>Define a New Long-Term Funding Model:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  The changes to the funding model are on purpose modest for the Reorganization, with the
	  intent provide more ability and freedom for the IETF to adjust its model later. However,
	  the subsidiary and independent organization models also clearly provide an opportunity
	  to define exactly what kind of agreements exist between the IETF and the new
	  organization. This is important in conveying the role of different parties to potential
	  sponsors, for instance.</t>

	  <t>Clarify Overall Roles and Responsibilities:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  The Reorganization is an opportunity to rethink what staff roles are needed,
	  staff levels, whether to organize a function as a staff function or as contracted
	  service to a vendor. All options are likely to provide clarified roles and responsibilities.
	  </t>

	  <t>Define Support Staff Roles and Responsibilities:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  As above.</t>

	  <t>Re-Define the Role of the IETF Community in Relation to
	  Administrative Activities:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  Again,  this is necessary in all the Reorganization options.
	  It is particularly important for the discussion of transparency.</t>

	  <t>Define Improved Transparency Requirements:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  An improvement can be provided in any chosen option, but it will require
	  (a) adopting the by default open model, (b) agreeing on a list of exceptions, as well as
	  obviously clear definition of roles.</t>

	  <t>Define a New IASA 2.0 Team:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  This will also be necessary in all options.
	  </t>

    </list></t>
    
    </section>
    
      <section title="Pros and Cons">

          <t><xref target="IASA-assess" /> highlights the pros and cons of the IASA++ option.</t>

          <texttable anchor="IASA-assess" style="all" title="IASA++ Pros and Cons">
            <ttcol align="left">Pros</ttcol>
            <ttcol align="left">Cons</ttcol>
            <c>Maintains familiar structures and relationships</c>
            <c>Does not provide the IETF with true independence of funding or staff from ISOC;
	    lack of clarity inherent in two organizations controlling resources may remain</c>
            <c>Start-up costs limited to those associated with hiring additional staff</c>
            <c>Creates risk that challenges present in the current IASA will not actually be solved or will
            re-emerge over time</c>
            <c>Does not require legal and administrative work to incorporate a new entity</c>
            <c>Potentially requires ISOC to cede more authority to the IETF community or increase
            transparency beyond ISOC's comfort zone</c>
            <c>Allows IETF to continue to rely on ISOC to somewhat frictionlessly compensate for
            budget shortfalls if necessary</c>
            <c>Continuing confusion about alignment between ISOC and IETF on policy and standards matters.</c>
          </texttable>

          <t><xref target="Subsidiary-assess" /> highlights the pros and cons of the ISOC subsidiary
          option.</t>

          <texttable anchor="Subsidiary-assess" style="all" title="ISOC Subsidiary Pros and Cons">
            <ttcol align="left">Pros</ttcol>
            <ttcol align="left">Cons</ttcol>
            <c>Forces some delineation of responsibility, staff, and funds between the IETF and ISOC</c>
            <c>Leaves open some potential for continued lack of clarity about authority and funding
            between the IETF and ISOC</c>
            <c>Provides the IETF community with greater authority over IETF administration</c>
            <c>Potentially requires ISOC to cede more authority to the IETF community or increase
            transparency beyond ISOC's comfort zone</c>
            <c>Can leverage existing ISOC legal structures and personnel to keep administrative work
            required to incorporate subsidiary to a minimum</c>
            <c>Requires legal and administrative work to incorporate subsidiary</c>
            <c>Requires less IETF community volunteer time commitment to administrative matters than
            current IASA</c>
            <c>Vests more decision-making authority in paid staff than under current IASA</c>
            <c>Allows IETF to continue to rely on ISOC to somewhat frictionlessly compensate for
            budget shortfalls if necessary</c>
            <c>Start-up costs include costs of incorporating the subsidiary and re-organizing/hiring
            additional staff</c>
            <c>Allows IETF to continue to leverage expertise of ISOC administrative personnel</c>
            <c>Continuing confusion about alignment between ISOC and IETF on policy and standards matters.</c>
          </texttable>

          <t><xref target="Independent-assess" /> highlights the pros and cons of
          the independent organization option.</t>

          <texttable anchor="Independent-assess" style="all" title="Independent Organization Pros and Cons">
            <ttcol align="left">Pros</ttcol>
            <ttcol align="left">Cons</ttcol>
            <c>Eliminates all ambiguity about IETF having authority independent from
            ISOC over staff, funds, and decisions</c>
            <c>Start-up costs include legal and administrative costs to incorporate
            a new entity, hire new staff, transfer contracts and funds</c>
            <c>Provides the IETF community with potentially complete authority over
            IETF administration and funding</c>
            <c>ISOC's financial support for the IETF may be viewed as more tenuous
            if the IETF is a legally separate entity from ISOC</c>
            <c>Requires less IETF community volunteer time commitment to
            administrative matters than current IASA</c>
            <c>Ability for the IETF to rely on ISOC in the event of budget
            shortfalls may be more limited</c>
            <c>Allows for direct investment in small number of professional staff
            specifically tailored to the IETF's needs and culture, while continuing
            to rely heavily on contractors</c>
            <c>Vests more decision-making authority in paid staff than under current
            IASA</c>
            <c>Provides opportunity to structure board in such a way to overcome
            current challenges with IAOC structure</c>
            <c>Requires more from board members than what is currently required of
            IAOC insofar as hiring and evaluating staff</c>
            <c>Removes need for alignment between ISOC and IETF on policy and standards matters.</c>
            <c>Requires IETF to assume legal risk currently assumed by ISOC</c>
          </texttable>

        </section>

      <section title="Financial Impacts">

	<t>There are several different classes of financially-relevant changes.
	Funding-related changes have been covered in <xref target="funding"/>, as have transition
	costs.</t>

	<t>All the suggested models imply some actual increases in expenditure and
	financial resources on an ongoing basis. The following applies
	generally to all chosen models:</t>

	<t>The increases are due to, for instance, shifting
	more work to staff and contractors. For the staff changes, the primary position
	actually being added is having both Executive Director and Operations Director,
	instead of one IAD. We've already had a Legal Counsel and roles similar to the
	Director of Fundraising and Communications Director. These chances coincide with
	other personnel changes in IASA, as the experienced, long-term
	IAD is retiring and a long-term IETF Legal Counsel is also
	changing.</t>

	<t>It is also expected that the
	role of the Legal Counsel will also increase, e.g., in terms of reviewing
	contracts.</t>

	<t>For both the subsidiary model or the independent
	organization model, there can be additional and potentially
	significant costs. For example, having a full-time
	communications director on staff means paying the person's
	full salary, health insurance, worker's compensation, sick
	pay, etc. In general, while under the ISOC model the IETF may
	have been able to take a particular percentage of a person's
	base costs, under a more independent arrangements the IETF
	is an employer and liable for all associated costs at 100%.
	Similarly, some current contracted or volunteer roles, if
	turned to staff positions, can increase costs.</t>

	<t>Audits, payroll, HR, office space, equipment - these are things we do
	not currently account for in the IETF budget, that we wouldn't have to
	pay for as a subsidiary (assuming we can share overhead with ISOC,
	since that's part of the point), but that we would have to pay for as
	an independent org.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Other Impacts">

        <t>Depending on the chosen option, volunteers are needed for either different roles than
        today (the board) or for both different roles and more volunteers (the board and the
        advisory council).</t>

        <t>It is for further study whether current IETF leadership (e.g., IAB Chair) should
        continue to be part of these boards or councils.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Conclusions" anchor="conc_recs">

      <t>While there are some initial conclusions in the analysis in
      the previous sections, clearly more work is needed. In
      particular, we request and welcome thoughts and contributions
      from the IETF community, particularly regarding any potential
      missed options or the implications of options being considered
      here.</t>

	    <section title="Transition Plan" anchor="transition">

	      <t>Following feedback we receive before and during the
	      IETF-100 meeting, we will develop a detailed transition
	      plan and include that here. We can then seek feedback on
	      the transition plan between the 100th and 101st IETF
	      meetings, with the goal of an actionable recommendation
	      for how to effect the transition presented at
	      IETF-101.</t>

	      <t>The transition plan should address items such as the
	      following (and we seek suggestions on areas we may have
	      missed):

	      <list style="symbols">
		<t>Volunteer organization transition plan and
		timeframe</t>
		<t>Legal, financial, and administrative actions</t>
		<t>Staffing actions (e.g. job descriptions)</t>
		<t>Documentation actions (e.g. roles and
		responsibilities, updates to RFCs)</t>
		<t>Near-term goals for the new board (e.g. develop and
		release a budget within 90 days of formation)</t>
		<t>Other</t>
	      </list>
	      </t>
	    </section>

	  </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="acks">

      <t>This text is the work of the design team, but greatly influenced by discussions in
      the IETF community. The team would in particular like to thank Alissa Cooper,
      Andrew Sullivan, Ray Pelletier, Ted Hardie, Gonzalo Camarillo, Brian Carpenter,
      Lucy Lynch, Stephen Farrell, Dave Crocker, Jon Peterson, Alexa Morris,
      Michael Richardson, Olaf Kolkman, Kathy Brown, and Melinda Shore for interesting
      discussions in this problem space.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4071.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.daigle-iasa-retrospective.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.hall-iasa20-workshops-report.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.arkko-ietf-iasa-thoughts.xml" ?>
      <reference anchor="Camarillo">
        <front>
          <title>ISOC to cover potential re-structuring costs related to IASA 2.0</title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Camarillo"></author>
<date month='September' year='2017 (https://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/ietf/current/msg104265.html)'/>
        </front>
        <format type='HTML'
		target='https://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/ietf/current/msg104265.html'/>
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
